"Hepatitis E Virus in Pork"
You've probably heard
of hepatitis A,
which you can get from
eating unsanitary food
in the developing world.
Then, we discovered hepatitis B,
which is spread by infected
blood and bodily fluids.
And then, hepatitis C,
mostly from IV drug use.
These days
we're up to hepatitis E,
which is actually the main cause
of viral hepatitis worldwide.
It was first discovered
in the early 80s,
but we didn't have a clue
where it was coming from
until 1997,
when it was discovered
in more than 90 percent
of tested U.S. pig farms.
From the
viral hepatitis division
of the Centers for
Disease Control and Prevention,
the CDC:
"Much meat; much malady."
Hepatitis E
is now considered a zoonosis,
an animal-to-human disease
that causes 20 million
human cases a year,
primarily from pigs
via the consumption
of infected pork products.
The hepatitis E virus
has since been detected
on pig farms worldwide,
including 80 to 100 percent
of U.S. operations,
where it's spread
via the fecal-oral route.
So, no surprise there's such
widespread infection
on industrial
confinement operations
given how closely
packed together the animals are.
Though if you test the pigs
where it counts,
in terms of food safety
at the slaughterhouse,
only six percent of U.S. pigs
have active infections,
meaning infectious virus
flowing through
their bloodstreams
at the time of slaughter.
At a retail level,
about 10 percent of commercial
pork products tested worldwide
contain the hepatitis E virus,
found in pork meat, and sausage,
as well as organ meats
like the liver,
with the highest rates
found in North America.
So, for example, in California,
though only
12 percent of samples
were positive for the virus,
most of the retail packages had
at least one positive sample,
so most were infected
with hepatitis E.
Perhaps this helps explain
why there's
an even tighter correlation
between pork consumption
and liver cirrhosis
than there is between
alcohol consumption
and liver cirrhosis
on a country-by-country basis.
But just because there's
infectious virus in retail meat,
does that mean
it could survive cooking?
Unfortunately,
it seems that some virus
would most likely survive
the internal temperatures
of rare-cooked meat.
So, how can we avoid infection?
According to the former chief of
the CDC's viral hepatitis lab,
the most expedient way
to prevent meats,
organ meats, or seafood
from conveying hepatitis
is to avoid eating them,
or in the very least ensuring
that they are thoroughly cooked
before being consumed.
Unfortunately,
in addition to the potential
for the hepatitis E virus to
survive some cooking processes,
raw blood products
are commonly used
in ready-cooked foods like ham.
Porcine blood--pig's blood--
used as an ingredient
in meat products
may serve as a vehicle
for hepatitis E transmission.
Blood components are ingredients
used by the meat industry
as color enhancers
or emulsifiers,
and surprisingly,
none of these blood products
appears to be heat treated
prior to being processed
into food.
The virus was found
in 90 percent
of liquid blood products,
and 30 percent
of powdered blood.
That helps explain why
the incidence of hepatitis E
is significantly lower
among blood donors
who don't eat meat,
indicating that meat consumption
is a major risk factor
for hepatitis E infection,
with those eating pork products
like ham or bacon
at about triple the odds
of infection.
Though some studies found
no cases of infection
among vegetarians,
others just showed a
significantly lower prevalence.
How might vegetarians
be getting hepatitis E?
It could be
through dairy products.
Cows can become infected
with the virus too,
and their milk contaminated
with infectious hepatitis E
is now recognized
as a new potential
for high risk of transmission
to humans.
Even when infected milk
has been fully pasteurized,
it was still found
to be infectious.
But, the most likely cause
of hepatitis E infection
in vegetarians
may be other people.
Once we're infected
through our dietary habits,
we can transmit it to others
via not washing our hands
after using the bathroom,
or potentially in the bedroom,
though this has not yet
been confirmed.